<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://djt97.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://djt97.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2025-04-02T21:00:55+11:00</updated><id>https://djt97.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Economist. 27. Dad of 3. Trying to build something. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Do Economists Care About Lying?</title><link href="https://djt97.github.io/blog/2025/do-economists-care-about-lying/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Economists Care About Lying?"/><published>2025-04-02T09:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2025-04-02T09:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://djt97.github.io/blog/2025/do-economists-care-about-lying</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://djt97.github.io/blog/2025/do-economists-care-about-lying/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p><em>(Note: This is a bit of an esoteric post based on an idea that came up when working on research about communication games— see <a href="/projects/targeted_persuasion">Targeted Persuasion</a>.)</em></p> <p>My goal here is to show you two economic models of communication which are the same from a consequentialist perspective, but different from the perspective of our (or at least <em>my</em>) moral intuitions. I will then make the case that this is not just some abstract distinction, but that it has real, practical, ethical and legal consequences. I did not think it would be difficult to convince people that these two models are importantly different, until I started talking about this with economic theorists. I hope I will not have to convince <em>you</em> that they are different, but let’s see.</p> <p>This all started when I saw two models of communication that an economic theorist told me were “the same”. I’ve written this post in such a way that it should be readable for anyone, including those who have no familiarity with communication games or even with economics. So let’s jump into the two models, and a specific communication strategy under which these are considered “the same”.</p> <h2 id="the-models">The Models</h2> <p>I am selling a product which has some unknown quality denoted by $q$. The quality can either be good ($q=G$) or bad ($q=B$). If the product is good quality you would prefer to buy it. If it is bad quality you would prefer not to. Hence you will only buy the product if you believe that it is good quality with sufficiently high probability.</p> <p><strong>Model 1.</strong> I learn the true quality of the product. Then, knowing the quality, I send you one of two messages $m$: I either say</p> <ol> <li>“the quality is good” ($m=g$), or</li> <li>“the quality is bad” ($m=b$).</li> </ol> <p>If the quality is good ($q=G$), then I will always send you $m=g$. If the quality is bad ($B$), I toss a fair coin and only send you $m=b$ if it lands tails. Otherwise, if it lands heads I send you $m=g$. You then decide whether to purchase the product.</p> <p>The basic idea here is that if I learn the product is good quality, I’ll always tell you the truth. But if I learn it’s bad quality, I’ll only tell you the truth half the time. So if (for example) you observe the message $m=b$, you know for sure that the product must be bad quality (for, if it were good quality, I would have sent you $m=g$). Economic theorists will recognize this as the kind of strategy which is typical in models of <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~gentzkow/research/BayesianPersuasion.pdf">Bayesian Persuasion</a>.</p> <p><strong>Model 2.</strong> An autonomous machine learns the true quality of the product. If the product is good quality, the machine will always send me $m=g$. If the product is bad quality, the machine will toss a fair coin and send me $m=b$ if it lands tails, otherwise it will send me $m=g$. Once I have received the message, I <em>pass the message directly on to you</em> and then you decide whether to purchase the product.</p> <h2 id="why-the-models-are-the-same-and-different">Why the models are the same, and different</h2> <p>The reason these two models are considered “the same”, is that the rational beliefs about the product conditional on observing the message $m=b$ or $m=g$ are identical in both. In particular, if you observe $m=b$, then you infer that with certainty the product is of bad quality. If you observe $m=g$, then you infer that with some probability (let’s say $\tau$) the product is of good quality, and with probability $1-\tau$ it is of bad quality but the coin toss landed heads. As long as $\tau$ is large enough, you will buy the product whenever you observe $m=g$.</p> <p>Since beliefs determine actions, and actions determine payoffs, the two models lead to identical <em>outcomes</em>. It is in this sense— the consequential sense— that they are the same. But I hope you can see why I find this unsettling— there seems to me something fundamentally different between the two models: In Model 1, I have the ability to <em>lie</em>, in Model 2 I do not. In Model 1, I am informed; in Model 2, I am a messenger. We do hold people (morally, legally) responsible for lying to us, but we all know that you don’t shoot the messenger.</p> <h2 id="where-does-this-leave-us">Where does this leave us?</h2> <p>Thankfully there are economists taking these ideas seriously. <a href="https://econweb.ucsd.edu/~jsobel/">Joel Sobel</a> (who many economic theorists would know from the seminal paper by <a href="https://www.brown.edu/Departments/Economics/Faculty/Glenn_Loury/louryhomepage/teaching/Ec%20237/Crawford%20and%20Sobel%20(Ecta%201982).pdf">Crawford &amp; Sobel, 1982</a> which developed the “cheap-talk” communication model) wrote a paper titled “<a href="https://par.nsf.gov/servlets/purl/10143200">Lying and Deception in Games</a>” in which he offers one formalization of what it means to lie in a communication game. Unfortunately his model does not encapsulate the difference between Model 1 and Model 2— since his “Sender” (the equivalent of my “seller”) always knows the state. In fact, Sobel points exactly this out on page 941 of the paper under the heading “Imperfect Knowledge of the State”. He says that if the seller has imperfect knowledge of the “state” (the quality $q$), then it would be natural to define lying in terms of what the seller communicates about the message(s) they <em>observe</em>, rather than having to communicate the true quality (since they may not know what the actual quality is). And indeed, if we extend the definition of lying in this natural way then the seller in Model 1 has the ability to lie, while the seller in Model 2 does not, in agreement with our intuition.</p> <h2 id="why-we-should-care">Why we should care</h2> <p>The distinction between Model 1 and Model 2 becomes important in a world that is increasingly mediated by algorithms. When you receive a product recommendation, a news article, or a tailored advertisement, you’re often receiving the output of a system that has been designed to maximize some objective function—for example, the profit of the system’s owner.</p> <p>If the algorithm “learns” to lie in a way that is optimal for the seller, who bears the responsibility? For example, a medical diagnosis algorithm might occasionally provide false negatives to reduce health care costs. Is this meaningfully different from a doctor who occasionally lies about test results for the same reason? In both cases, the outcome is identical— some sick patients go untreated. But the mechanisms— and our intuitions about moral responsibility— differ dramatically.</p> <p>Or what about an algorithmic credit score system that systematically discriminates against certain populations to maximize bank’s profit? The algorithm creates a shield of plausible deniability. This is the difference between Model 1 and Model 2.</p> <p>An uncomfortable possibility is that as we delegate more decision-making to algorithms, we may be inadvertently creating systems that implement Model 1-type strategies (strategic lying) while maintaining the moral and legal protections of Model 2 (mere message passing). “You can’t shoot the messenger” becomes a useful shield when the messenger is a complex algorithm whose inner workings remain inscrutable—even to its creators. As such, we need to think carefully about the incentives for firms in designing these systems, and whether we can create a framework that holds them accountable for the outcomes of their algorithms.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>The seemingly abstract distinction between our two models ultimately reveals something about how we assign moral responsibility in communication. When outcomes are identical but mechanisms differ, our intuitions suggest that <em>process</em> matters—not just results. It matters not just for moral reasons, but for legal ones too.</p> <p>How then, should economists think about the differences in mechanism which are outcome-equivalent? Perhaps more importantly, how do we develop ethical and legal frameworks that properly account for these distinctions? This is, in some sense, <em>not</em> a new discussion in economics. We abstract from processes and focus on outcomes. But processes are important, and good research highlights exactly when or why they are important, and allows us to design policy accordingly.</p> <p>Great work is being done specifically on the topic of developing a framework for AI liability, see for example <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.clsr.2023.105794">this paper</a>, <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/26810851">this paper</a>, or <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10711067/">this medical review</a>. But as far as I can tell, very little has been done on the economics of lying in the context of algorithms. I think this would be a really interesting area to explore.</p> <p>DJ</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="economics"/><category term="economics"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="lying"/><category term="algorithms"/><category term="communication games"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When do processes matter more than outcomes?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Memorize First, Understand Later?</title><link href="https://djt97.github.io/blog/2025/memorize-first-understand-later/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Memorize First, Understand Later?"/><published>2025-01-31T09:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T09:00:00+11:00</updated><id>https://djt97.github.io/blog/2025/memorize-first-understand-later</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://djt97.github.io/blog/2025/memorize-first-understand-later/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>I recently listened to a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QTI69kKeaC4&amp;t=4520s">live session</a> with <a href="https://andymatuschak.org/">Andy Matuschak</a> and <a href="https://josephnoelwalker.com/">Joe Walker</a> in which Andy takes a look “under the hood” at Joe’s podcast preparation process, asks a number of questions, and provides some useful advice. I really enjoyed it— there’s been some buzz around <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/SXJGSPeQWbACveJhs/the-best-tacit-knowledge-videos-on-every-subject">“tacit-knowledge vidoes”</a> recently, and this was a perfect example.</p> <p>A bit over a year ago I started taking my memory practice seriously. Over the recent holiday break I was talking with some family and friends about how changing my memory practice has completely revolutionized my learning and by extension, my research. To my dismay, no-one seemed all that interested. It’s not that people are uninterested because they don’t care about learning, I think they’re uninterested simply because they don’t have a memory practice and so they don’t understand its value— it honestly feels like a superpower. But as with any superpower, one has to learn how to control it (c.f. Clark Kent, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0279600/">Smallville seasons 1-10</a>).</p> <hr/> <h2 id="understanding-before-memorization">Understanding Before Memorization</h2> <p>So it’s safe to say that I am interested in good memory practice. About a year ago I skim-read Andy’s article on <a href="https://andymatuschak.org/prompts/">“How to write good prompts”</a> and watched one of his live note-taking sessions. I also read Michael Nielsen’s <a href="https://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html">“Augmenting Cognition”</a>, but that basically comprised the extent of what I knew about spaced repetition outside of personal experience. I certainly hadn’t read Piotr Wozniak’s <a href="https://www.supermemo.com/en/blog/twenty-rules-of-formulating-knowledge">“Twenty rules of formulating knowledge”</a>— in fact, I hadn’t even heard of Piotr Wozniak. But during the interview between Andy and Joe the following excerpt stood out, precisely because it really <em>did not</em> resonate with me:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>WALKER:</strong> … one rule of thumb I have is I won’t write a prompt on something that I don’t understand.</p> <p><strong>MATUSCHAK:</strong> Yeah. Actually, I learned a lot from Piotr Wozniak’s 20 rules of effective space repetition flashcard writing and his number one suggestion is: understand before you memorize.</p> </blockquote> <p>“Understand before you memorize.” I mean it <em>sounds</em> right. Wozniak points out that one could plausibly memorize an entire German history textbook without knowing German— claiming “The value of such knowledge is negligible.” I’m not about to suggest you should go and memorize an entire textbook (in any language), but I do want to claim that memorizing things that you don’t understand is not only forgivable, but that it can be helpful for learning.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-mental-bookmark">The Mental Bookmark</h2> <p>Let me emphasize that my comments are based <em>entirely</em> on my own experience, and I do not know whether there is much (if any) research on what I am suggesting here. I would love nothing more than for someone like Andy Matuschak or Michael Nielsen to explain exactly the shortcomings of my claims below.</p> <p>I have found that memorization before understanding can be helpful because it acts as a <em>mental bookmark</em>. Imagine you are reading a complex book. You might come across a term or concept you don’t understand, but you have a feeling that it’s important for later. Instead of stopping your flow to decipher it immediately (which can be disruptive), you place a physical bookmark (sticky note, book-tab) at that page. You continue reading, trusting that the context will become clearer later. Your memory prompt is like that bookmark, but for your mental landscape. It marks a spot you intend to return to, once you have the appropriate context.</p> <p>Mental bookmarks are particularly helpful when you encounter a key fact or concept whose understanding hinges on underlying ideas you have not yet grasped. The conventional approach in this case would be to first go and understand the component parts, and then to build up to the target understanding. This “understand-first” approach makes a lot of sense if you think of <em>learning as building</em>. You need to lay a solid foundation of understanding, or anything you build on top will be fragile and unstable.</p> <p>But sometimes (though not always) learning is less like constructing a building and more like solving a jigsaw puzzle. Imagine trying to assemble a 1000pc jigsaw <em>without</em> seeing the picture on the box. For a long time, you’d just have scattered, seemingly unrelated pieces. In fact, when solving a jigsaw, you <em>often</em> refer back to the box so that you know roughly where each piece goes. In a ‘puzzle’ model of learning, you don’t initially know where all the pieces go, but you begin by getting a sense of the overall picture and <em>then</em> you begin to fill in the pieces.</p> <p>So what if you did the following?: memorize the very thing you aim to understand <em>first</em>— (that is, create a mental bookmark). In doing this, you recognize that you don’t understand its content <em>yet</em>, but the bookmark contains all of the component pieces that you’re about to go and attempt to understand. If you’re using spaced repetition, the mental bookmark also becomes a scheduled check-in on your knowledge gaps. What I am suggesting here is that sometimes <em>remembering what you want to remember</em> is just as important as understanding it.</p> <p>And after all, isn’t the whole point of having a memory practice to remember the things that you want to remember?</p> <p><img src="https://media1.tenor.com/m/s1c7kF_LE3QAAAAd/harry-potter-neville-longbottom.gif" alt="Harry Potter Neville Longbottom GIF"/></p> <hr/> <h2 id="a-simple-example-from-michael-nielsen">A Simple Example from Michael Nielsen</h2> <p>Let me give a simple example where memorizing first and understanding later can be helpful. I’ll borrow <a href="https://cognitivemedium.com/srs-mathematics">Michael Nielsen’s example</a>. Suppose you want to memorize the theorem: “a complex normal matrix is always diagonalizable by a unitary matrix.” This might as well read “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colorless_green_ideas_sleep_furiously">colorless green ideas sleep furiously</a>” if you’ve never heard the terms “diagonalizable”, “unitary” or “normal” (which turns out to be anything <em>but</em> normal), but the specific content of the theorem is not crucial to the example I am making here.</p> <p>Nielsen describes how he wrote his Anki cards in two phases. In the first phase, he writes cards that help him understand the proof of the theorem. In the second phase he writes cards to help him push the boundaries on his understanding of the theorem.</p> <p>I’d like to suggest a phase 0:</p> <div class="anki-card-example"> <strong>Add Card:</strong> <br/> {{c1:: a complex normal matrix}} is always {{c2::diagonalizable by a unitary matrix}}. </div> <p>(For those who don’t know, this is the format for a <em>cloze deletion</em> card in Anki).</p> <p>And you can actually do this <em>before</em> you begin phase I or phase II or phase XXVII or however you structure your process of understanding. In fact, this can <em>help</em> you orient your phase I— now you know what you don’t know.</p> <p>And if in two weeks’ time, this card seems like something that is no longer worth understanding, then you should delete it and be done with it! But this is unlikely to happen since the reason you created the memory prompt in the first place was that you <em>knew</em> this was something that you wanted to understand.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="ok-i-lied-and-a-word-of-warning">Ok, I Lied (and a word of warning)</h2> <p>Although I made it sound like Andy and Joe would disagree with me on this, Joe makes exactly this point in the next breath following the excerpt I quoted earlier:</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>WALKER:</strong> Right. Having said that maybe there’s one little exception to that though which is for definitional things. I might write prompts even if I don’t fully understand all of the contours of the underlying concept. And it’s still helpful because even if I’m slowly, stochastically learning this concept, I’m still picking up the language and it’s making the eventual understanding easier.</p> </blockquote> <p>YES. This is <em>exactly</em> right. But the conversation moved on immediately after this, and I thought this point deserved some exposition, which is why we’re here.</p> <p>The beauty of memorizing first is that it can accelerate the learning process. By having the ‘answer’ or the key fact already in your memory before understanding every detail, you create a mental hook for new information to attach to. When you later beginning putting the pieces of the puzzle together, you’re not starting without a picture. That being said, if you simply memorize and never return to these prompts to fill the gaps in your understanding, then Wozniak’s warning about meaningless knowledge becomes valid. The mental bookmark is only useful if you eventually turn the page.</p> <p>I’m interested to hear whether other people have had this experience too. Please feel free to reach out to me if you have any thoughts on the role of memorization in learning and understanding!</p> <p>Happy bookmarking,</p> <p>DJ</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="learning"/><category term="memory"/><category term="learning"/><category term="spaced-repetition"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is learning like building a house, or solving a puzzle?]]></summary></entry></feed>